<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rfc version="3" category="exp" docName="draft-wang-jep-judgment-event-protocol-06" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>Judgment Event Protocol (JEP)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-wang-jep-judgment-event-protocol-06"/>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Wang" fullname="Yuqiang Wang">
      <address><email>signal@humanjudgment.org</email><uri>https://github.com/hjs-spec</uri></address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="May" day="4"/>
    <abstract><t>This document defines the Judgment Event Protocol (JEP), a neutral
verifiable event format for decision-related operations in human,
organizational, software, and autonomous agent systems.

JEP specifies four immutable event verbs: Judgment (J), Delegation (D),
Termination (T), and Verification (V). It defines a signed JSON event
structure, anti-replay fields, detached JSON Web Signature (JWS)
verification over JSON Canonicalization Scheme (JCS) canonicalized
payloads, event hash and reference semantics, validation levels,
structured validation results, failure codes, extension handling,
trust-profile interfaces, and determinability boundaries.

JEP is intended to provide a global protocol-level interoperability
layer for verifiable decision event records. JEP-Core does not define
legal liability, authorization validity, regulatory compliance,
organizational trust decisions, global identity, global truth, or
mandatory support for any specific credential, identity, AI platform,
agent framework, or blockchain system.</t></abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true"><name>A Neutral Verifiable Event Format for Agent Decisions</name><t>### draft-wang-jep-judgment-event-protocol-06</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[Author: Yuqiang Wang  
Intended status: Experimental  
Version: -06 working draft  
Companion drafts:
- draft-wang-jep-profiles-00
- draft-wang-jep-conformance-00]]></sourcecode>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>Companion Drafts</name><t>This draft defines JEP-Core. Optional interoperability bindings are
defined in `draft-wang-jep-profiles-00`. Schemas, test vectors,
validation-result structure, and reference-validator behavior are defined
in `draft-wang-jep-conformance-00`.</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>1. Introduction</name><t>Autonomous and semi-autonomous agent systems increasingly make, assist
with, delegate, terminate, verify, or record decisions across
organizational, platform, model, and jurisdictional boundaries. These
systems need a minimal and interoperable way to record decision-related
events so that later verifiers can determine whether a particular event
payload existed, whether it was signed under an applicable trust profile,
whether it was modified, whether it refers to other events or evidence,
and which validation level has been reached.</t>
<t>JEP addresses this need by defining a compact signed JSON event format.
The format is intentionally narrow: it records an event verb, actor
identifier, timestamp, claim or digest, nonce, optional audience,
references, extensions, and signature. More complex identity,
credential, policy, archival, evidence, or causal-chain semantics are
externalized to profiles, extensions, HJS-like archival layers, or
JAC-like chain-composition layers.</t>
<t>JEP records verifiable protocol facts. It does not by itself prove
external target facts. In partially observed systems, a signed event log
can support audit and accountability workflows without guaranteeing
complete or zero-error determination of external facts.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>2. Protocol Objective and Non-Goals</name><t>### 2.1 Objective</t>
<t>JEP-Core defines a neutral event layer for verifiable judgment-related
acts. A conforming JEP event can support determination, subject to the
applicable validation mode and trust profile, that:</t>
<t>1. an event payload existed;
2. the event payload was signed as specified;
3. the payload was bound to an actor identifier under a trust profile;
4. the event carried a timestamp, nonce, optional audience, and optional
   references or extensions;
5. references, event hashes, and critical extensions were processed
   according to JEP-Core rules;
6. a verifier reached a declared validation level.</t>
<t>### 2.2 Non-Goals</t>
<t>JEP-Core does not define:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- legal liability;
- moral responsibility;
- regulatory compliance;
- global truth determination;
- external target-fact determinability;
- authorization delegation validity;
- permission-chain enforcement;
- lifecycle state-machine enforcement;
- a global identity framework;
- a global credential framework;
- a global trust framework;
- mandatory DID, VC, X.509, OAuth, RATS, blockchain, or AI-platform
  support;
- confidentiality for event content;
- long-term storage, redaction, retention, or disclosure policy;
- causal-chain or responsibility-graph computation.]]></sourcecode>
<t>A JEP event records claims about judgment-related acts. It MUST NOT be
presented as proof that the underlying real-world assertion is true
unless an applicable external profile and evidence policy makes that
determination.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>3. Design Principles</name><t>JEP-Core follows these principles:</t>
<t>1. **Core minimality:** JEP-Core defines the stable narrow-waist event
   layer.
2. **Identity-system neutrality:** JEP-Core MUST NOT require any
   specific identity system.
3. **Credential-system neutrality:** JEP-Core MUST NOT require VC or any
   other credential model.
4. **Platform neutrality:** JEP-Core MUST NOT require any AI platform,
   agent framework, cloud provider, or blockchain network.
5. **Profile-based interoperability:** identity, credentials,
   attestation, authorization, and archival policy are handled by
   optional profiles.
6. **Layered verification:** syntax, cryptographic validity,
   actor-binding, chain validation, and policy validation are separate.
7. **Explicit determinability boundary:** protocol validity is not the
   same as external truth.
8. **Privacy by minimization:** sensitive evidence SHOULD be referenced
   by digest or controlled evidence mechanisms rather than embedded in
   event payloads.
9. **Extension without semantic capture:** extensions MUST NOT redefine
   JEP-Core semantics.
10. **Algorithm agility:** cryptographic algorithms are selected by JOSE
    headers, conformance profiles, and trust profiles rather than by
    event verbs.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>4. Requirements Language</name><t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
when, and only when, they appear in all capitals.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>5. Terminology</name><t>**Actor:** The entity identified by `who` that is claimed by the event.
An actor MAY be a human, organization, model, agent, tool, service,
device, workflow, committee, session, swarm, human-agent composite, or
organization-agent composite.</t>
<t>**Signer:** The key holder that produces the event signature. The signer
is not necessarily identical to the actor. The binding between signer and
actor is defined by a trust profile.</t>
<t>**Subject:** The entity or object about which a decision, delegation,
termination, or verification is made. A subject is distinct from the
actor.</t>
<t>**Event:** A single immutable signed JSON object representing one
judgment-related act.</t>
<t>**Unsigned Event:** A JEP event object with the `sig` member omitted.</t>
<t>**JEP Signing Payload:** The UTF-8 octets of the JCS-canonicalized
unsigned event.</t>
<t>**Event Hash:** An algorithm-tagged digest over the full signed event.</t>
<t>**Claim:** Semantic content carried by `what` or by an extension.</t>
<t>**Reference:** A cryptographic or typed pointer to another event, chain,
digest, credential, policy, evidence, context, archive receipt, or
external object.</t>
<t>**Trust Profile:** A profile that defines actor identifier forms,
signing-key resolution, actor/key binding, revocation, historical
validity, acceptable algorithms, and related evidence policy.</t>
<t>**Validation Level:** The highest validation stage completed by a
verifier.</t>
<t>**Validation Mode:** The context in which validation is performed, such
as acceptance, archival, chain, or policy review.</t>
<t>**Verification Scope:** The declared scope of a V event, such as syntax,
cryptographic, actor-binding, chain-integrity, credential-status, policy
compliance, human review, external evidence, factual claim, or archival
integrity.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>6. Core Event Object</name><t>A JEP event is a JSON object. Producers MUST emit I-JSON-compatible JSON
and MUST NOT emit duplicate JSON member names. Verifiers MUST reject
events containing duplicate JSON member names.</t>
<t>The top-level members are:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[| Member | Status | Description |
|---|---|---|
| `jep` | REQUIRED | Wire-format major version. For this draft, `"1"`. |
| `verb` | REQUIRED | One of `"J"`, `"D"`, `"T"`, `"V"`. |
| `who` | REQUIRED | Actor identifier claimed by the event. |
| `when` | REQUIRED | Actor-supplied event timestamp, Unix seconds. |
| `what` | Conditional | Claim object, descriptor, or algorithm-tagged digest. |
| `nonce` | REQUIRED | Replay-protection nonce. |
| `aud` | RECOMMENDED | Intended audience or validation context. |
| `ref` | Conditional | Typed reference or event hash reference. |
| `ext` | OPTIONAL | Extension object. |
| `ext_crit` | OPTIONAL | Critical extension identifier list. |
| `sig` | REQUIRED | Detached signature container. |]]></sourcecode>
<t>The top-level extensibility mechanism is `ext`. Producers SHOULD NOT add
new top-level members outside this specification unless defined by a
future JEP revision or a registered extension that explicitly updates the
top-level object.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>7. Field Semantics</name><t>### 7.1 `jep`</t>
<t>The `jep` member identifies the wire-format major version. For this
draft, the value is `"1"`.</t>
<t>`JEP-Core-0.6` identifies the specification release version. It is not
the wire-format version. The wire-format value `jep: "1"` can remain
stable across multiple draft revisions and release versions when the
core event object remains wire-compatible.</t>
<t>A verifier MUST NOT infer Internet-Draft revision number or release
maturity solely from the `jep` member.</t>
<t>### 7.2 `verb`</t>
<t>The `verb` member identifies the event verb. It MUST be one of `J`, `D`,
`T`, or `V`.</t>
<t>Event verbs do not determine cryptographic algorithms, storage policy,
privacy mode, identity method, or legal effect.</t>
<t>### 7.3 `who`</t>
<t>`who` identifies the actor claimed by the event.</t>
<t>`who` is not necessarily:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- the signer;
- a legal person;
- the controller of the key;
- a real-world identity;
- the subject of the decision.]]></sourcecode>
<t>The binding between `who` and the signing key is determined by the
applicable trust profile.</t>
<t>### 7.4 `when`</t>
<t>`when` is an actor-supplied event timestamp in Unix seconds. JEP-Core
does not by itself prove wall-clock time. Stronger time evidence requires
a timestamping, receipt, archival, transparency, or storage profile.</t>
<t>Implementations SHOULD distinguish:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- event time;
- signature time;
- receipt time;
- archive time;
- verification time;
- policy-evaluation time.]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 7.5 `what`</t>
<t>`what` carries the event claim, digest, descriptor, or report. It records
what the actor asserted, judged, delegated, terminated, or verified. It
does not by itself prove external truth.</t>
<t>When represented as an object, `what` SHOULD use semantic subfields such
as:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `claim`;
- `subject`;
- `scope`;
- `result`;
- `evidence`;
- `context`.]]></sourcecode>
<t>When represented as a digest, the digest MUST be an algorithm-tagged
digest string.</t>
<t>### 7.6 `nonce`</t>
<t>`nonce` supports replay protection. Nonce uniqueness is evaluated within
an actor, audience, trust-profile, and replay-window context. JEP-Core
does not require global nonce uniqueness.</t>
<t>### 7.7 `aud`</t>
<t>`aud` indicates intended audience or validation context. It does not by
itself enforce access control. Access control, retention, redaction, and
disclosure policy are outside JEP-Core.</t>
<t>### 7.8 `ref`</t>
<t>`ref` is a reference field. A reference does not by itself imply
endorsement, truth, authorization validity, or causality.</t>
<t>References MAY identify:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- event;
- chain;
- digest;
- credential;
- policy;
- evidence;
- context;
- archive receipt;
- external object.]]></sourcecode>
<t>A simple event reference SHOULD use the event hash of the referenced JEP
event.</t>
<t>### 7.9 `ext` and `ext_crit`</t>
<t>`ext` contains named extension objects. `ext_crit` contains the
identifiers of critical extensions. Unknown critical extensions MUST
cause validation failure. Unknown non-critical extensions MAY be ignored.</t>
<t>### 7.10 `sig`</t>
<t>`sig` carries the detached signature container. JEP-Core uses detached
JWS over the JCS-canonicalized unsigned event unless another registered
signature profile applies.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>8. Event Verb Semantics</name><t>### 8.1 J — Judgment</t>
<t>A Judgment event records that an actor made, accepted, produced,
approved, selected, rejected, ranked, classified, or otherwise committed
to a decision-related claim.</t>
<t>A J event MUST NOT be interpreted as proof that the judged claim is true.</t>
<t>Typical uses include:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- model output approval;
- human approval;
- risk classification;
- tool-selection decision;
- policy decision;
- recommendation acceptance;
- evidence assessment.]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 8.2 D — Delegation</t>
<t>A Delegation event records that an actor delegated a task, authority,
responsibility, capability, or decision context to another actor or
system.</t>
<t>A D event SHOULD identify, directly or by reference:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- delegator;
- delegatee;
- scope;
- constraints;
- expiry;
- context;
- termination conditions.]]></sourcecode>
<t>A D event records a delegation claim. It does not by itself prove legal
authorization or external enforceability.</t>
<t>### 8.3 T — Termination</t>
<t>A Termination event records that a previous delegation, authority,
session, capability, workflow context, verification context, or chain
reliance is ended, revoked, expired, superseded, or no longer valid for
future reliance.</t>
<t>A T event MUST identify the terminated target and termination scope.</t>
<t>A T event does not delete historical events, erase past facts, or
automatically revoke external legal authority. It affects future reliance
according to JEP-Core rules and applicable profiles.</t>
<t>### 8.4 V — Verification</t>
<t>A Verification event records that an actor performed a validation, audit,
review, confirmation, rejection, or verification action over an event,
chain, digest, subject, credential, policy, evidence, or external object.</t>
<t>A V event MUST declare its verification scope. A V event MUST NOT imply
verification beyond its declared scope.</t>
<t>Initial verification scopes include:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `syntax`;
- `cryptographic`;
- `actor_binding`;
- `chain_integrity`;
- `extension_processing`;
- `credential_status`;
- `policy_compliance`;
- `human_review`;
- `external_evidence`;
- `factual_claim`;
- `archival_integrity`.]]></sourcecode>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>9. References and Chains</name><t>A JEP reference proves only that one event payload cryptographically or
semantically referenced another object. It does not prove causality,
endorsement, truth, authorization, or completeness.</t>
<t>A JEP reference does not by itself imply causality. Causal interpretation
is defined by JAC or another chain profile.</t>
<t>A reference chain proves linkage between observed event objects. It does
not prove that the observed log is complete, append-only, or free from
omission unless a profile explicitly declares and supports a complete-log
assumption.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>10. Algorithm-Tagged Digest Strings</name><t>JEP uses algorithm-tagged digest strings for event hashes, content
digests, and reference digests.</t>
<t>Syntax:</t>
<t>```text
&lt;hash-algorithm&gt;:&lt;lowercase-hex-digest&gt;
```</t>
<t>The hash algorithm identifier MUST be lower-case ASCII. The digest value
MUST be lower-case hexadecimal.</t>
<t>Implementations conforming to JEP-Core-0.6 MUST support `sha256`.</t>
<t>Example:</t>
<t>```text
sha256:3a6eb0790f39ac87c94f3856b2dd2c5d110e6811602261a9a923d3bb23adc8b7
```</t>
<t>Additional digest algorithms MAY be defined by conformance profiles,
trust profiles, or registered extensions.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>11. Event Hashes and Signing Input</name><t>The JEP signing input is the unsigned event object with `sig` omitted,
canonicalized using JCS and encoded as UTF-8 octets.</t>
<t>The event hash identifies the full signed event object, including `sig`.</t>
<t>For the default hash profile:</t>
<t>```text
event_hash = sha256(UTF8(JCS(full_signed_event)))
```</t>
<t>The signing input and event hash are intentionally different:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- signing input excludes `sig`;
- event hash includes `sig`.]]></sourcecode>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>12. Signature, Hash, and Algorithm Agility</name><t>JEP-Core preserves algorithm agility.</t>
<t>A JEP event is protected by a detached JWS signature over a
JCS-canonicalized unsigned event payload.</t>
<t>JEP-Core does not assign cryptographic algorithms to event verbs. J, D,
T, and V share the same cryptographic processing model.</t>
<t>The concrete signature algorithm, key type, hash algorithm, and algorithm
acceptability policy are determined by JOSE headers, conformance
profiles, and trust profiles.</t>
<t>JEP-Core semantics are algorithm-neutral. A JEP-Core implementation
MUST NOT assign algorithms to event verbs or treat algorithm choice as
part of the semantics of J, D, T, or V.</t>
<t>A baseline conformance class MAY define a required-to-implement
algorithm set for interoperability. For compatibility with the -05
baseline, an Ed25519/JWS/JCS conformance class MAY be defined by the
companion conformance draft. Such a conformance class does not make
Ed25519 the only algorithm allowed by JEP-Core semantics.</t>
<t>A trust profile MUST define which algorithms are acceptable for a given
deployment context.</t>
<t>A verifier MUST reject an event if the declared algorithm is unsupported,
prohibited by the applicable profile, inconsistent with the resolved key
type, inconsistent with the signature container, or inconsistent with a
critical cryptographic extension.</t>
<t>A verifier SHOULD distinguish real-time acceptance validation from
archival validation. An algorithm MAY be acceptable for archival
validation while being prohibited for new event signatures.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>13. Trust Profile Interface</name><t>JEP-Core does not define a global identity or trust framework.</t>
<t>A trust profile MUST define:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- supported actor identifier forms;
- key identifier syntax and discovery;
- binding rules between `who` and signing keys;
- accepted signature algorithms;
- downgrade policy;
- key rotation handling;
- revocation handling;
- historical key validity;
- credential or attestation use, if any;
- policy evaluation hooks, if any.]]></sourcecode>
<t>Support for DID, VC, X.509, OAuth, RATS, blockchain anchoring, or any
specific identity system is OPTIONAL and MUST NOT be required for
JEP-Core conformance.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>14. Validation Model</name><t>### 14.1 Validation Levels</t>
<t>JEP validation is divided into five levels:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[| Level | Name | Meaning |
|---|---|---|
| 0 | Syntax | JSON, I-JSON, required fields, schema shape. |
| 1 | Cryptographic | Canonicalization, event hash, detached signature. |
| 2 | Actor Binding | Key bound to actor under trust profile. |
| 3 | Chain | References, critical extensions, replay, termination effects, chain integrity. |
| 4 | Policy | Domain, legal, organizational, regulatory, or deployment policy. |]]></sourcecode>
<t>A verifier MUST report the highest successfully completed validation
level. A verifier MUST NOT present Level 1 cryptographic validity as
Level 4 policy validity.</t>
<t>A JEP event MAY be cryptographically valid but policy-invalid.</t>
<t>### 14.2 Validation Modes</t>
<t>Initial validation modes are:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `acceptance`;
- `archival`;
- `chain`;
- `policy`.]]></sourcecode>
<t>Acceptance validation checks freshness and replay. Archival validation
MUST NOT reject an event solely because its timestamp is outside the
current freshness window.</t>
<t>### 14.3 Deterministic Validation Algorithm</t>
<t>A verifier SHOULD process an event in this order:</t>
<t>1. parse JSON;
2. reject duplicate JSON member names;
3. check required top-level fields;
4. check verb-specific field requirements;
5. remove `sig` to construct unsigned event;
6. canonicalize unsigned event using JCS;
7. verify detached signature;
8. compute event hash if needed;
9. resolve actor/key under trust profile;
10. check actor/key binding;
11. check nonce and freshness for acceptance mode;
12. validate `aud` if present and relevant;
13. resolve and validate references if applicable;
14. process critical extensions;
15. apply chain rules, including termination effects;
16. apply optional policy rules;
17. return structured validation result.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>15. Validation Result Object</name><t>A verifier SHOULD return a structured validation result.</t>
<t>Example:</t>
<t>```json
{
  "valid": true,
  "level": 3,
  "mode": "archival",
  "profile": "jep-core-0.6",
  "scopes": ["syntax", "cryptographic", "actor_binding", "chain_integrity"],
  "event_hash": "sha256:...",
  "warnings": [],
  "errors": []
}
```</t>
<t>Validation results MUST distinguish:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- cryptographically valid but policy-invalid;
- archivally valid but not acceptable for new reliance;
- valid under profile A but invalid under profile B;
- signature-valid but actor-binding invalid;
- chain-valid under observed-log assumptions only.]]></sourcecode>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>16. Failure Codes</name><t>A conforming validator SHOULD return structured failure codes.</t>
<t>### 16.1 Syntax Errors</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `ERR_INVALID_JSON`
- `ERR_DUPLICATE_MEMBER`
- `ERR_UNSUPPORTED_JEP_VERSION`
- `ERR_UNKNOWN_VERB`
- `ERR_MISSING_REQUIRED_FIELD`
- `ERR_INVALID_FIELD_TYPE`
- `ERR_INVALID_TIMESTAMP`]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 16.2 Cryptographic Errors</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `ERR_CANONICALIZATION_FAILED`
- `ERR_CANONICALIZATION_VERSION_UNSUPPORTED`
- `ERR_INVALID_EVENT_HASH`
- `ERR_UNSUPPORTED_SIGNATURE_ALG`
- `ERR_PROHIBITED_SIGNATURE_ALG`
- `ERR_ALG_KEY_TYPE_MISMATCH`
- `ERR_ALG_PROFILE_MISMATCH`
- `ERR_HASH_ALG_UNSUPPORTED`
- `ERR_SIGNATURE_CONTAINER_INVALID`
- `ERR_SIGNATURE_MISSING`
- `ERR_SIGNATURE_INVALID`
- `ERR_DIGEST_MISMATCH`
- `ERR_ARCHIVAL_ALG_STATUS_UNKNOWN`
- `ERR_ALG_DEPRECATED_FOR_NEW_EVENTS`]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 16.3 Actor and Trust Errors</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `ERR_ACTOR_UNRESOLVED`
- `ERR_KEY_UNRESOLVED`
- `ERR_KEY_NOT_BOUND_TO_ACTOR`
- `ERR_KEY_REVOKED`
- `ERR_KEY_NOT_VALID_AT_EVENT_TIME`
- `ERR_TRUST_PROFILE_UNSUPPORTED`]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 16.4 Replay and Freshness Errors</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `ERR_NONCE_REPLAY`
- `ERR_EVENT_EXPIRED`
- `ERR_TIMESTAMP_OUT_OF_WINDOW`]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 16.5 Reference and Chain Errors</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `ERR_REF_UNRESOLVED`
- `ERR_REF_HASH_MISMATCH`
- `ERR_CHAIN_BROKEN`
- `ERR_DELEGATION_SCOPE_EXCEEDED`
- `ERR_TERMINATED_REFERENCE_REUSED`
- `ERR_CYCLE_DETECTED`
- `ERR_COMPLETE_LOG_ASSUMPTION_UNSATISFIED`]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 16.6 Extension Errors</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `ERR_UNKNOWN_CRITICAL_EXTENSION`
- `ERR_EXTENSION_SCHEMA_INVALID`
- `ERR_EXTENSION_VALIDATION_FAILED`
- `ERR_EXTENSION_CONFLICT`]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 16.7 Policy Errors</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- `ERR_POLICY_REJECTED`
- `ERR_AUTHORIZATION_CONTEXT_MISSING`
- `ERR_DOMAIN_REQUIREMENT_UNSATISFIED`]]></sourcecode>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>17. Extension Rules and Conflict Handling</name><t>An extension MUST declare:</t>
<t>1. extension identifier;
2. extension version;
3. JSON schema or equivalent data model;
4. whether it may be critical;
5. validation requirements;
6. security considerations;
7. privacy considerations;
8. interaction with event hashes and signatures;
9. interaction with other known extensions, if applicable.</t>
<t>Extensions MUST NOT redefine the semantics of core JEP members.</t>
<t>Unknown critical extensions MUST cause rejection. Unknown non-critical
extensions MAY be ignored.</t>
<t>If two critical extensions impose inconsistent requirements, validation
MUST fail with `ERR_EXTENSION_CONFLICT`.</t>
<t>Extension identifiers SHOULD be collision-resistant. Supported forms
include:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- reverse-DNS identifiers, e.g. `org.example.jep.profile.vc`;
- URI identifiers;
- registered short names;
- experimental `x-*` identifiers.]]></sourcecode>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>18. Conformance Requirements</name><t>A JEP-Core-0.6 producer MUST support:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- I-JSON-compatible event construction;
- required top-level fields;
- JCS canonicalization of unsigned payloads;
- detached JWS signature generation under at least one conformance class;
- algorithm-tagged digest strings;
- nonce generation;
- `ext` and `ext_crit` semantics.]]></sourcecode>
<t>A JEP-Core-0.6 verifier MUST support:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- duplicate-member rejection;
- core field validation;
- JCS canonicalization;
- detached signature verification under at least one conformance class;
- event hash calculation;
- validation levels;
- structured validation result object;
- unknown critical extension rejection;
- acceptance and archival validation modes.]]></sourcecode>
<t>A JEP-Core-0.6 implementation MUST NOT require support for any optional
identity, credential, attestation, blockchain, AI platform, or agent
framework profile.</t>
<t>### 18.1 Baseline Algorithm Conformance</t>
<t>For interoperability with earlier JEP drafts, a baseline conformance
class MAY require support for detached JWS using JCS canonicalization,
`sha256` algorithm-tagged digest strings, and Ed25519 verification.</t>
<t>This baseline is a conformance-class requirement, not a JEP-Core semantic
requirement. Other profiles MAY define additional or alternative
algorithm suites, including regional, enterprise, COSE/CBOR, composite,
or post-quantum profiles, provided that their algorithm identifiers,
key representations, downgrade policies, and validation behavior are
specified.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>19. Determinability Boundary</name><t>JEP distinguishes observable protocol facts from external target facts.</t>
<t>### 19.1 Observable Protocol Facts</t>
<t>JEP can support determination of protocol-level facts such as:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- whether a payload was signed by a key;
- whether a key is acceptable under a trust profile;
- whether an event hash matches an event payload;
- whether an event references another event;
- whether a nonce has been seen within a replay window;
- whether a critical extension was processed;
- whether a delegation was later terminated in the observed log.]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 19.2 External Target Facts</t>
<t>JEP alone does not determine external target facts such as:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- whether a real-world statement is true;
- whether a model internally understood a request;
- whether an actor is legally liable;
- whether a delegation is legally enforceable;
- whether a human actually read a document;
- whether a physical-world action occurred outside the logged system.]]></sourcecode>
<t>A profile MAY define evidence rules for external target facts. Such rules
are outside JEP-Core.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>20. Observed Log Assumptions</name><t>An observed JEP log is not necessarily a complete log.</t>
<t>Absence of an event in an observed log MUST NOT be interpreted as proof
that the event did not occur unless a complete-log assumption is
explicitly declared by the deployment profile.</t>
<t>Profiles MAY define:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- complete-log profile;
- partial-log profile;
- selective-disclosure log;
- redacted log;
- archive-backed log;
- transparency-backed log.]]></sourcecode>
<t>A chain reconstruction result MUST declare whether it relies on complete
or partial log assumptions.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>21. Relationship to HJS and JAC</name><t>JEP defines atomic signed judgment events.</t>
<t>HJS-like systems manage storage, receipt, archival context, retention,
redaction, selective disclosure, privacy policy, and evidence lifecycle
for JEP events. HJS MUST NOT redefine JEP-Core event semantics,
signature semantics, event hash semantics, validation levels, or failure
codes.</t>
<t>JAC-like systems compose JEP events into causality chains,
responsibility chains, delegation paths, verification paths, and
workflow accountability graphs. JAC MUST NOT redefine JEP-Core event
format, signature semantics, event hash semantics, or validation levels.</t>
<t>A JEP reference does not by itself imply causality. Causal interpretation
is defined by JAC or another chain profile.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>22. Security Considerations</name><t>JEP-Core mitigates:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- payload tampering;
- signature forgery under supported algorithms;
- replay within configured windows;
- reference hash mismatch;
- unknown critical extension processing;
- basic chain integrity failures.]]></sourcecode>
<t>JEP-Core does not by itself prevent:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- compromised signing keys;
- false claims signed by legitimate actors;
- omission of relevant events from a log;
- collusion among actors;
- legal or organizational misuse;
- incorrect external evidence;
- malicious trust profiles;
- timestamp manipulation without external time evidence.]]></sourcecode>
<t>### 22.1 Downgrade Resistance</t>
<t>A verifier MUST reject algorithms prohibited by the applicable profile. A
verifier MUST NOT accept a weaker algorithm merely because it is
syntactically valid in JOSE.</t>
<t>### 22.2 Human-in-the-Loop Semantics</t>
<t>A human-review event records that a human actor emitted or endorsed a
review-related claim. It does not prove that the human fully understood
the underlying material, that the decision was correct, or that legal
compliance was satisfied.</t>
<t>### 22.3 AI Actor Semantics</t>
<t>JEP-Core does not mandate any specific AI actor identity scheme. AI
actor identity, model identity, tool identity, service identity, and
session identity are defined by trust profiles or extensions.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>23. Privacy Considerations</name><t>JEP events may reveal actor identity, subject identity, decision timing,
delegation structure, organizational workflow, tool usage, and audit
relationships.</t>
<t>Deployments SHOULD minimize personal data in `what` and extensions. When
possible, external evidence SHOULD be referenced by digest rather than
embedded directly.</t>
<t>Digest references may enable correlation, confirmation attacks, or
dictionary attacks. Sensitive evidence references MAY require salted
digests, commitment schemes, access-controlled evidence stores,
audience-bound references, selective disclosure, or redaction.</t>
<t>JEP signatures and references may create linkability across contexts.
Implementations SHOULD avoid reusing actor identifiers across unrelated
audiences unless required by the trust profile.</t>
<t>JEP is an accountability protocol component. It SHOULD NOT be deployed as
a general monitoring mechanism without data-minimization, retention,
access-control, and redaction policies.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>24. Registry Considerations</name><t>JEP registries SHOULD cover:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- verbs;
- extension identifiers;
- verification scopes;
- validation modes;
- error codes;
- trust profile identifiers;
- conformance class identifiers;
- algorithm policy labels.]]></sourcecode>
<t>New verb registrations are NOT RECOMMENDED. New verbs require an update
to JEP-Core explaining why existing verbs plus extensions are
insufficient.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>25. Versioning and Compatibility</name><t>Minor versions MAY add optional fields or optional extensions. Major
versions MAY change validation requirements.</t>
<t>Unknown critical extensions MUST cause validation failure. Unknown
non-critical extensions MAY be ignored.</t>
<t>Unknown required core fields MUST cause validation failure unless defined
by a future compatible revision.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>26. Examples</name><t>### 26.1 Minimal Judgment Event Shape</t>
<t>```json
{
  "jep": "1",
  "verb": "J",
  "who": "did:example:agent-789",
  "when": 1742345678,
  "what": "sha256:aa55ad4393538f14e6b4961de1a29216eed93517cb6c2631a56a5ee75edb3b7a",
  "nonce": "f47ac10b-58cc-4372-a567-0e02b2c3d479",
  "aud": "https://platform.example.com",
  "ref": null,
  "sig": "..."
}
```</t>
<t>Full test vectors are defined in the companion conformance draft.</t>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>27. Changes from -05</name><t>Major changes from `draft-wang-jep-judgment-event-protocol-05`:</t>
<sourcecode><![CDATA[- Reframed JEP-Core as a neutral narrow-waist event infrastructure.
- Added explicit protocol objective and non-goals.
- Added design principles.
- Added detailed field semantics for `who`, `when`, `what`, `nonce`,
  `aud`, `ref`, `ext`, and `sig`.
- Expanded J/D/T/V semantics.
- Added verification-scope requirements for V events.
- Added validation levels.
- Added structured validation result object.
- Added structured failure-code taxonomy.
- Added deterministic validation algorithm.
- Added extension conflict handling.
- Added trust profile interface.
- Added determinability boundary.
- Added observed-log assumptions.
- Added relationship to HJS and JAC.
- Added human-in-the-loop and AI actor semantic boundaries.
- Added downgrade-resistance language.
- Moved concrete DID/VC/X.509/OAuth/RATS profile material to
  `draft-wang-jep-profiles-00`.
- Moved schema, test vectors, and reference validator behavior to
  `draft-wang-jep-conformance-00`.]]></sourcecode>
<t>---</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>Author's Address</name><t>Yuqiang Wang  
Email: signal@humanjudgment.org  
URI: https://github.com/hjs-spec</t></section><section numbered="true"><name>v0.6 Direct Upgrade Note</name><t>This document is part of the JEP v0.6 draft set. The v0.6 set directly
incorporates standardization structure, interoperability profiles,
conformance artifacts, schemas, signed test vectors, invalid cases, and
multi-language validator seeds without changing the JEP-Core narrow-waist
semantics.</t></section>
  </middle>
</rfc>
